<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Scott Sandman's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[A blog detailing my learning experiences on the path to becoming a Full Stack Developer]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Apr 2020 00:58:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[Knock, Knock, Knock, Penny]]></title><description><![CDATA[Using a simple tap() for debugging curried functions]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/knock-knock-knock-penny/knock-knock-knock-penny/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/knock-knock-knock-penny/knock-knock-knock-penny/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 17 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./knock-knock-knock-penny.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of Knock, knock, knock, Penny&quot; title=&quot;We&amp;#x27;ve all been there&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ve all been there. That place where ever word and sound sends us further down the rabbit hole. Most certainly we will be there again. Hopefully what I&apos;m about to share with you will help limit how bad &quot;there&quot; gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, I was going to call this posting &quot;Tap, Tap, Tap&quot; (you&apos;ll see why later), but as I was musing, &quot;knock, knock, knock, Penny&quot; kept coming to mind. The entire series of them. Then I found the image and here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently our class at JRS Code School took a dive into Functional Programming (FP). Im not going to get to deep into defining FP. For those of you not familiar with FP and would like to learn more I recommend bookmarking this post or adding to it your RSS feed and heading over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://fpjs.now.sh/docs/contents&quot;&gt;Functional Javascript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;ve made it this far, then there is a strong possibility that you have at some point struggled with a curried function. I struggled mightily with a few until being introduced to this tiny little tap function. Let&apos;s take a look at a curried function and then I&apos;ll show you how tap works. The following curried function uses Ramda functions compose, reduce, sort and map to return an array of a deck of playing cards in face value order. The compose function reads the other functions from right-to-left (if you prefer left-to-right you can use pipe) so the deck of cards array is passed into the map function which creates a new array of the card objects key &quot;code&quot;, which is then passed to sort to (obviously) sort it and finally it is passed to reduce where a new array of the card objects is returned in sorted order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./curried-function.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of curried function&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above function currently works, but at one time it did not. How did I debug it? By using a function called tap. Let&apos;s take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./tap-function.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of tap function&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the three taps? That&apos;s why the draft title of this post was Tap, Tap, Tap. But, you can call it whatever you like. Tap just seems a fitting name as it taps into the sequence of curried functions and gets called in the sequence along with the other functions. Here&apos;s a look at it put into action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;./curried-function-with-tap.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Image of curried function with tap function inserted&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it do? Well, it simply accepts the return value of the previous function as a parameter, logs that parameter to the console and then returns that value to the next function allowing you to see the output at each step of the curried function. Pretty simple, right? It&apos;s been very helpful to me in understanding how a curried function works and how to alter my code accordingly to get the desired outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you can find use for this little tidbit. I know I have and in the process have limited the number of times I have had to look like dear, sweet Penny up above.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Great Gatsby]]></title><description><![CDATA[My First Venture into Gatsby and GraphQL]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/the-great-gatsby/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/the-great-gatsby/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Well, here we are. The first post of my recently constructed blog. How did we get here? It all started a couple weeks ago in JRS Code School video class session (pandemic and all). &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwpearce.com/&quot;&gt;Robert Pearce&lt;/a&gt;, a Senior Software Engineer, took some time out of his day to speak with us prospective developers. One of the items he touched on during our discussion was &quot;learning in public&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about what he meant by learning in public for a few days and was having a tough time wrapping my head around what it meant. Was I suppose to be on Facebook and Twitter all the time? I&apos;m not, by the way. So I reach out to Robert and asked. He responded with &quot;This will tell you everything you need to know: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swyx.io/writing/learn-in-public/&quot;&gt;https://www.swyx.io/writing/learn-in-public/&lt;/a&gt; &quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I clicked on the link and gained a much better understanding of what it meant to &quot;learn in public&quot;. It was something real and tangible and not just toodling around on social media. One of the first items on the list was to start a blog and discuss what I have been learning. Simple enough. I&apos;ve written blogs before. But where to start? Should I use my knowledge of MongoDB and Api&apos;s? We did just do a Travel Blog using those tools in class. I was having a difficult time figuring out how I was going to properly format the blog object when I passed it back into the HTML. I didn&apos;t really want it to be lumped all together and it didn&apos;t seem logical to have to write new JavaScript with each blog to format it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Robert, again. Robert&apos;s response, &quot;Start with HTML and CSS only and work your way up to using GatsbyJS.&quot; That&apos;s a quality plan. However, Robert doesn&apos;t really know me. You mention Gatsby to me once and it goes on my list of things to read about and eventually learn. Mention it twice and with the lure of working my way up to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I sat down to build a blog. Yes, using Gatsby. I found a tutorial online offered by Gatsby and I dug in. I should mention here that they also have a starter blog that you can clone from Github. That&apos;s not my style. A few hours in and I had broken it. The Blog that is. Errors everywhere. I&apos;m pretty certain I deleted some files and code I wasn&apos;t suppose to. Anyway, back to square one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took to Google again and that&apos;s when I found this tutorial by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ultimatecourses.com/blog/building-a-blog-with-gatsby-and-graphql&quot;&gt;Emma Bostian&lt;/a&gt;. Attempt number two was successful, obviously. But not only that, Emma did a really nice job of explaining ways to use GraphQl to set up your queries and handle your data. She didn&apos;t just show the code and explain it. She took the tutorial into GraphIQL and demonstrated how to build the queries. Kudos, Emma, that was very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did I learn in the past two days? Well, I reacquainted myself with ReactJS. It had been almost a year since I last worked on a project with it. Timing couldn&apos;t have been better as we are starting the React portion of our class this week. I learned that React with Gatsby and with GraphQL can make putting together a blog website fairly simple and eloquent. In more detail, I learned how to use my knowledge of APIs and turn them into a query. I learned how to set up those queries to be passed along into pages, and I also figured out how to navigate around in Gatsby a little bit. I liked it, a lot. This won&apos;t be my last adventure with it and most likely not the last time I break an app using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed the read. I do promise to get more technical as time goes on with actual code examples and such. I also plan on adding some more functionality to the app. In the meantime, if you have any comments or suggestions, please feel free to click on the Contact link above and shoot me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honor legendary news broadcaster Walter Cronkite, &quot;And that&apos;s the way it is, April 13th, 2020.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>