<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Scott Sandman's | Software Engineer]]></title><description><![CDATA[A blog detailing my learning experiences as a software developer]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io</link><generator>GatsbyJS</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Sep 2020 18:03:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><item><title><![CDATA[The Clone Series]]></title><description><![CDATA[Five Yard Penalty]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/clone-series-b/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/clone-series-b/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 13 Aug 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, I revealed that I was going to be working on a Slack clone to keep building on my skill set. It seems that has turned out to be a false start resulting in a five yard penalty. I was premature in trying to fit the clone project into my schedule. I did start the project and got a couple of days into planning and set-up before I realized I had quite a bit more to do in preparing for my volunteer teaching gig with Microsoft TEALS. I also felt I needed to be spending more time studying for the AWS Certification and then a job opportunity came about leading to research on the company and a bunch of interview prep (both for initial phone and in-person meetings). And then I lost most of a day at the doctors office dealing with a nagging back injury. I know. I get it. That&apos;s why I threw the flag on myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&apos;ve backed up the five yards, surveyed the defense and am now calling an audible. I hope to return to the clone some time next week, but that is dependent on how they respond to the last job interview. Turns out I may have secured a job and, afterall, that is the end goal. Until next time, stay healthy and safe.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Clone Series]]></title><description><![CDATA[A Series Detailing My Build of a Slack Clone]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/clone-series-a/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/clone-series-a/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Welcome back. A quick update before we get started. Since graduating from JRS, I attended my daughter&apos;s wedding in SLC. Wedding was great. Travel to and from, not so much. Upon returning to Charleston, I have been networking, taking classes and viewing talks on egghead, testing my skills at PluralSight (expert in Express.js and proficient in 7 other skills), prepping for my role as a volunteer teaching assistant for the Microsoft TEALS Program, and preparing to take the AWS Certified Developer Certification. AWS recommends working with their services for roughly a year before taking the certification. I&apos;m not that patient and have set a goal of 6 months. I&apos;ll keep you posted on how that goes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, on to today&apos;s topic: I&apos;m building a clone of Slack. Why? To keep building my skills, of course, and it seems like a solid challenge. I still have some architecture decisions to make, but going with my mainstay MERN stack and I&apos;ll throw some AWS services like Cognito, S3, and Lambda. I am definitely looking to go serverless and, to that end, am looking into utilizing a micro services approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan as it stands now is to post weekly updates on my progress and what I&apos;ve learned along the way. However, given the scope of the project, I think it&apos;s likely there will be weeks when there are multiple posts and also times when I get hung up on some tech and it takes some time to work through. Whatever the case, there&apos;s a project, there&apos;s a plan, and there will be some posts. Hope you can join me for the duration. Until next time, stay healthy.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[AWS Cognito Custom React Components]]></title><description><![CDATA[Creating custom AWS Cognito React.js components]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/cognito-custom-react-components/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/cognito-custom-react-components/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s been a little while since I have posted. Apologies for that. The last month has been a blur with developing our final group and personal projects for JRS Code School. Concurrently, I have also been developing a mobile app for a social media start-up and a web application framework with a headless content management system for the Krause Center for Leadership and Ethics at The Citadel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My final solo project went well. I deployed a web app using AWS Amplify Console which built the React client side through a connection with the GitHub repo. The server side was built using Node.js, Express.js and REST API&apos;s connected to a MongoDB Atlas database. I then implemented the serverless framework to deploy it to an AWS Lambda. Pretty cool, right? You can check out the project &lt;a href=&quot;https://master.d302zpp58vbn99.amplifyapp.com/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is leading to today&apos;s topic. While developing the final project, I was using AWS Amplify CLI and had set up authentication and authorization using Cognito: &lt;code&gt;amplify add auth&lt;/code&gt;. For the sake of brevity, we are going to start at this point. If you need help getting to this juncture, please check out this &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.amplify.aws/start/q/integration/react&quot;&gt;tutorial&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fastest way to get Cognito up and running is to utilize the withAuthenticator wrapper and pass it your root level component thusly:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-Javascript&quot;&gt;import React from &quot;react&quot;;
import { withAuthenticator } from &quot;@aws-amplify/ui-react&quot;;

const App = () =&gt; {
    return (
        &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;Awesome Content Here&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
    )
}

export default withAuthenticator(App)
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, just like that, we have our auth. So, we are finally at today&apos;s topic. Having used withAuthenticator on a couple of projects, I continued to run into an issue with having to hard refresh to get state certain state updates. I spent a number of hours researching for a solution and implemented multiple changes to the code. The issue occured using redux. I added an AppContainer and wrapped withAuthenticator around it. Still occured. Tried implementing React Hooks useState and useEffect in lieu of redux. Yup, didn&apos;t work. I then moved from the withAuthenticator to the AmplifyAuthenticator component similar to the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React from &quot;react&quot;;
import { AmplifyAuthenticator } from &quot;@aws-amplify/ui-react&quot;;

const App = () =&gt; {
    return (
        &amp;#x3C;AmplifyAuthenticator&gt;
            &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;Router and Components&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
        &amp;#x3C;/AmplifyAuthenticator&gt;
    )
}

export default App
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same result. Next step. Custom Cognito components. Importing Amplify Auth gives us access to over 30 methods that can be used to generate a custom auth flow. It&apos;s not difficult to follow the &lt;a href=&quot;https://aws-amplify.github.io/amplify-js/api/classes/authclass.html&quot;&gt;docs&lt;/a&gt; and implement these methods, but it is time consuming. Make certain, if you elect to go this route, to make components that can be easily re-used. And, yes, it worked. The application renders and re-renders based on state instantly started working as expected.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Below is an example of a custom SignIn component:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React, { useState } from &quot;react&quot;;
import { Auth } from &quot;aws-amplify&quot;;

const SignIn = ({ setLoggedIn }) =&gt; {
  const [username, setUsername] = useState(&quot;&quot;);
  const [password, setPassword] = useState(&quot;&quot;);

  const attemptSignIn = async () =&gt; {
    try {
      await Auth.signIn(username, password); //one of 30+ methods for custom auth flow
      setPassword(&quot;&quot;); // reset password to empty string after submission
      setLoggedIn(true); //setLoggedIn passed down from root component
    } catch (error) {
      console.error(error);
    }
  };

  const handleName = (e) =&gt; {
    setUsername(e.target.value);
  };

  const handlePassword = (e) =&gt; {
    setPassword(e.target.value);
  };

  return (
    &amp;#x3C;Container component=&quot;main&quot; maxWidth=&quot;xs&quot;&gt;
        input elements here...
    &amp;#x3C;/Container&gt;
  );
};

export default SignIn;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;SignOut is just a simple:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;Auth.signOut();
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throw in signUp, confirmSignUp, forgotPassword and you are well on your way to a fully customized auth flow using Cognito. Hope you learned something. Until next time, stay safe and healthy.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Smells Like Job Hunting Season]]></title><description><![CDATA[Time to put the skills to the test]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/job-hunting-season/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/job-hunting-season/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sniff. Sniff&lt;/em&gt; Smells like job hunting season. My time at JRS is coming to a close. It&apos;s been a fast paced two months and just like that we are working on final projects. Those new found skills (as well as the old ones) are getting put to the test. They are going to need to be sharp, too, given these recent economic times which have sent millions to the unemployment lines. Am I ready? That&apos;s for the potential employers to decide. My job is to continue to prepare and improve upon my skill sets and perhaps even add a few new ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed I did miss a few regular postings. That is because I have been doing what I stated above; preparing, studying, building a portfolio, generating new skills, fine-tuning the other ones and revamping my resume. One of the projects I have been working on is a mobile app. A local start-up here in Charleston asked for some help so I didn&apos;t hesitate. I had worked with React Native and Expo in the past (definitely rusty, though). So far I&apos;ve contributed by creating some placeholder screens, set up a pseudo authorization path, implemented the navigation stack with initial routes and got the redux started for handling user data. Looking forward to doing more. Especially with React Navigation. It has been completely re-vamped since I last used it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned earlier, it&apos;s also final project time at JRS. We started the group project yesterday and, after a slow start, got into a groove today and made some decent progress. We are building a student portal for future JRS students. The portal will have a place for assignments and resources to be posted along with an area for them to post about what they are learning (sound familiar). The client (our instructor, Mr. Casey Wilson) wanted to be sure we utilized the most skills possible so we are using Amazon Web Services Amplify framework which uses an S3 bucket to store images and documents, Dynamo to store resource postings, GraphQl as the API connecting the front end to S3 and Dynamo, RDS database for housing user profile data, Lambdas to implement REST APIs to communicate the user profile data to RDS, Cognito to handle authorization, with React carrying the front end, redux to manage the state the APIs are sending/receiving, Reach Router to get us to all that information and Material UI to make it look great. And, yes, that was a run-on. Had to channel some inner Kerouac to generate it. But that&apos;s not all. Mr. Wilson wanted to make sure we could also discuss all of the tools we are using on the project so he scheduled us to present at a local online meetup which will be attended by some of the best developers in our area. It reminds me of an interview I saw with NFL Hall of Fame kicker Morten Anderson. When asked if he ever felt pressure before any of his big kicks, he responded that he believed pressure was caused by having doubt and he never believed he couldn&apos;t make a kick. We got this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For my final project, I was true to myself and put forth a challenge that will push my skills to their limits and force me to add some new ones. I am writing a web application to assist small businesses in focusing their advertising on local clientele. Their are over 400,000 non-employer and small firms (under 20 employees) in South Carolina. They employ a large part of our work force and are responsible for a pretty good sized chunk of our job growth. We need them back on their feet as-soon-as possible. Any little bit I can do to help is well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The project is just coming out of the conceptual stage so I am still in the process of designing the architecture. The only things for certain are geo location services will be used and I will use React to frame up the front end. Hopefully, I will have some time next week to go into more detail. I do need to give a big shout out to Mr. Daniel Stern at the Harbor Entrepreneur Center. Mr Stern has gone out of his way to reach out to his small business contacts in hopes of having them beta test the application at the final presentation. Can&apos;t thank him enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s all I have time for today, but I will leave you with an interesting question I came across applying for a job today. One of the questions they asked along with the resume submittal was &quot;What makes you unique?&quot; I won&apos;t tell you what I wrote, but I will ask the same of you. Gotta love the round pegs in the square holes.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[React Hook - useEffect]]></title><description><![CDATA[Using React Hook useEffect to update state]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/react-useEffect/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/react-useEffect/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;In the last post, we discussed the use of React hooks in lieu of using the class method and props to manage and update state. To get a better understanding of the benefits of using hooks, we need to take another look at a class method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React from &quot;react&quot;

class App extends React.Component {
  constructor(props) {
    super(props)

    this.state = {
      firstName: &quot;Henry&quot;,
      lastName: &quot;Smith&quot;,
    }
  }
  render() {
    return (
      &amp;#x3C;div&gt;
        &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;First Name: {this.state.firstName}&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
        &amp;#x3C;h2&gt;Last Name: {this.state.lastName}&amp;#x3C;/h2&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;/div&gt;
    )
  }
}

export default App
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, a constructor is used to handle props, this.state is used to set initial values and this.state.firstName calls the state for rendering. Simple enough. But what if we want to manage the state throughout the lifecycle of our app? At this point we are talking about writing methods, getter methods, implementing this.setState() and using an assortment of predefined lifecycle methods such as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;componentWillMount()
componentDidMount()
componentWillUpdate()
componentWillUnmount()
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&apos;s getting quite a bit more involved now to set and manage our state; not to mention the amount of code is growing which means the chances of bugs is increasing. Enter the magic of hooks. If you recall from the previous post, useState not only allows us to set our state, but also defines an update method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React, { useState } from &quot;react&quot;

function App() {
  const [firstName, setFirstName] = useState(&quot;Henry&quot;)
  const [lastName, setLastName] = useState(&quot;Smith&quot;)

  return (
    &amp;#x3C;div&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;First Name: {firstName}&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h2&gt;Last Name: {lastName}&amp;#x3C;/h2&gt;
    &amp;#x3C;/div&gt;
  )
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point in the class method, we would need to begin adding all of our lifecycle methods to set and control state. Say hello to the hook, useEffect() which replaces them all. Yup, one hook to replace all of those predefined lifecycle methods. UseEffect takes two parameters; the first being a callback function. We&apos;ll talk about the second parameter in a moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React, { useState, useEffect } from &quot;react&quot;

function App() {
  const [firstName, setFirstName] = useState(&quot;&quot;)
  const [lastName, setLastName] = useState(&quot;&quot;) //initial state set to empty strings

  useEffect(() =&gt; {
    setFirstName(&quot;Henry&quot;)
    setLastName(&quot;Smith&quot;) //set state in useEffect
  })

  return (
    &amp;#x3C;div&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;First Name: {firstName}&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h2&gt;Last Name: {lastName}&amp;#x3C;/h2&gt;
    &amp;#x3C;/div&gt;
  )
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the example above, we set our initial states to empty strings and then updated them in useEffect() which executes when the page initially loads. This brings us to the second parameter. If we don&apos;t provide one, useEffect() will go into an infinite loop as it runs each time the app renders. By adding an empty array as a second parameter, we can tell useEffect to run only the single time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React, { useState, useEffect } from &quot;react&quot;

function App() {
  const [firstName, setFirstName] = useState(&quot;&quot;)
  const [lastName, setLastName] = useState(&quot;&quot;)

  useEffect(() =&gt; {
    setFirstName(&quot;Henry&quot;)
    setLastName(&quot;Smith&quot;)
  }, []) //use empty array to execute just once

  return (
    &amp;#x3C;div&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;First Name: {firstName}&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h2&gt;Last Name: {lastName}&amp;#x3C;/h2&gt;
    &amp;#x3C;/div&gt;
  )
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, if we want useEffect() to monitor our state, we simply need to tell it which state items to watch. We do this by adding them into the second parameter array. Then, anytime there is a call to update the state we are monitoring, useEffect() will execute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-JavaScript&quot;&gt;import React, { useState, useEffect } from &quot;react&quot;

function App() {
  const [firstName, setFirstName] = useState(&quot;&quot;)
  const [lastName, setLastName] = useState(&quot;&quot;)

  useEffect(() =&gt; {
    setFirstName(&quot;Henry&quot;)
    setLastName(&quot;Smith&quot;)
  }, [firstName, lastName]) //monitors for changes

  return (
    &amp;#x3C;div&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h1&gt;First Name: {firstName}&amp;#x3C;/h1&gt;
      &amp;#x3C;h2&gt;Last Name: {lastName}&amp;#x3C;/h2&gt;
    &amp;#x3C;/div&gt;
  )
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a pretty simple example of useEffect(), but I think it demonstrates enough to show its ease of use and elegance. Add in the fact useEffect() reduces the amount of code we have to generate, I&apos;m all for it. How about you?&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[React Hooks]]></title><description><![CDATA[Using React Hooks as an Alternate to Classes and Props]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/react-hooks/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/react-hooks/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 28 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Last week at JRS Code School, we began building web applications with React. In a lot of ways, this was a refresher for me, having taken an online mobile app development course which utilized React Native. But, as mostly is the case, there are multiple solutions to every problem. In the aforementioned class and other classes I have taken, the approach has been to use Object Oriented Programming (OOP) utilizing the Class structure. However, for the past several weeks, our studies at JRS have been focused on using a functional approach as our solutions. React hooks fit nicely into that approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, let&apos;s take a look at a class method which uses props and state:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 643px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/8c7e9bc7c200a18d971f73e0af395e0f/b5bda/class-ex1.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 63.190184049079754%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAANCAIAAAAmMtkJAAAACXBIWXMAABJ0AAASdAHeZh94AAABGUlEQVQoz42Sy27DIBBF/RuJwTwG8xxMjNPgLJqqi0pd9/8/prhp1UUVl6MLC8SFmQtdGoMNyXj00jgQfoSB0E0NdMJOPHhhosIMEbmzMkXhjBQNZumSXm54eU3lZowXQjIpGOdNN9d9AgxoKyQce0IJGSjd1GLmErA8X94/8LQUdE5BtQ5tdAPjYL2esgKFWgnOW63VjN5brTjdmvy1MVbHNrNdc/BuncsItv+CkNp2T/pN/fFQB6VkLzDlkou5npLSZKyWOhhMOkxufgqnVLNkjD94qor2cS5LzutaUk46nuP5GnJZXt7O1wImsAd0oEYYTY3tXjat/JRN+sPWxU7ZIOSfRfYtxv5JO5qIGicdxwm5gsbvcecTVXZlgEClal0AAAAASUVORK5CYII=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Class example with props and state&quot;
        title=&quot;Class example with props and state&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/8c7e9bc7c200a18d971f73e0af395e0f/b5bda/class-ex1.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/8c7e9bc7c200a18d971f73e0af395e0f/222b7/class-ex1.png 163w,
/static/8c7e9bc7c200a18d971f73e0af395e0f/ff46a/class-ex1.png 325w,
/static/8c7e9bc7c200a18d971f73e0af395e0f/b5bda/class-ex1.png 643w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 643px) 100vw, 643px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see, the class method uses a constructor to handle the props and set the initial state for firstName and lastName which are then called by this.state.firstName and this.state.lastName.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let&apos;s take a look at how we can do this using hooks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 640px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/f4fc5b78949e395a38ecba3b0f987cdd/6af66/hooks-ex1.png&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 49.69325153374233%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/png;base64,iVBORw0KGgoAAAANSUhEUgAAABQAAAAKCAIAAAA7N+mxAAAACXBIWXMAABJ0AAASdAHeZh94AAABEklEQVQoz4WQ607EIBBG+xxLYbjfBii1rrZGjT98/2dythpj3K6ewARIPuZkBqvt5Euqc8joQsjLGnJCl7ILNVqlFAgBIKheMwiQQmmQ0hoAfhrZifNxHBkb2bifLhc6cH4Qlkrr1OP0uK7LdL53uRgfXUKfqjOutdRqbsGjd0BtfoVBcFDGhBZSL+trat2lEtocccIczw+1F7xLFA7X7gNto0xL3UjL2IkWaZL8pz//wYE2ACgJJuSQW4qxFBJGX6ZYZ3qUUgnBxQ2+wi7VtmzLsmzbOm/P/eW9P715nCRN+zYDUNIYpS39z3Yutvu8qYo/GbRWMVgppAJqQxLfUwHxH4NRFi0Wj+iwtWyMPpzNIR8veU/n2ddzZwAAAABJRU5ErkJggg==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Hooks example with useState()&quot;
        title=&quot;Hooks example with useState()&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/f4fc5b78949e395a38ecba3b0f987cdd/6af66/hooks-ex1.png&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/f4fc5b78949e395a38ecba3b0f987cdd/222b7/hooks-ex1.png 163w,
/static/f4fc5b78949e395a38ecba3b0f987cdd/ff46a/hooks-ex1.png 325w,
/static/f4fc5b78949e395a38ecba3b0f987cdd/6af66/hooks-ex1.png 640w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 640px) 100vw, 640px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, I imported and deconstructed the hook useState from React. Then I simply set up a const variable in the form of an array which takes the variable name and a method to update that variable and set that equal to the hook useState where I was able to set the initial value for firstName. LastName is set up exactly the same way. Now, instead of having to use this.setState to update firstName or lastName, I simply just need to implement the method:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;setFirstName(&quot;Hank&quot;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&apos;s all for this iteration. Next up I will dive into the hook useEffect. After that, we&apos;ll check out redux. Yet another solution to handling state.
Until then, I&apos;ll leave you with the following quote by John Wooden, &quot;It&apos;s what you learn after you know it all that counts.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[Knock, Knock, Knock, Penny]]></title><description><![CDATA[Using a simple tap function for debugging curried functions]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/knock-knock-knock-penny/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/knock-knock-knock-penny/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 299px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/32dacb8dd6581c7d5c5e2da8d024e7e5/f6c98/knock-knock-knock-penny.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 56.44171779141104%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFwABAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAMCBP/EABUBAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAB/9oADAMBAAIQAxAAAAHgs0RRJ//EABwQAAICAgMAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAECAxEAEhMhMv/aAAgBAQABBQLkamkFlsXx1UgG/wD/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAVEQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEf/aAAgBAgEBPwFX/8QAGxAAAgIDAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEhIgIRkTH/2gAIAQEABj8CRXR6KFwVceDg/8QAHBAAAgICAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBMSFBYYGh/9oACAEBAAE/IUUa0L3Tky0Elkl3CRMeErTo/9oADAMBAAIAAwAAABDnP//EABYRAQEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEAEf/aAAgBAwEBPxARLL//xAAXEQEAAwAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEVFx/9oACAECAQE/ENRp/8QAHhABAAICAQUAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQARITFBUWGBweH/2gAIAQEAAT8QXVkCy9PmPoT7ltM+4zVGiiocheyG3lI74Ki/CYeBjAo0cE//2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image of Knock, knock, knock, Penny&quot;
        title=&quot;We&amp;#39;ve all been there&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/32dacb8dd6581c7d5c5e2da8d024e7e5/f6c98/knock-knock-knock-penny.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/32dacb8dd6581c7d5c5e2da8d024e7e5/d2f63/knock-knock-knock-penny.jpg 163w,
/static/32dacb8dd6581c7d5c5e2da8d024e7e5/f6c98/knock-knock-knock-penny.jpg 299w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 299px) 100vw, 299px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&apos;ve all been there. That place where ever word and sound sends us further down the rabbit hole. Most certainly we will be there again. Hopefully what I&apos;m about to share with you will help limit how bad &quot;there&quot; gets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Originally, I was going to call this posting &quot;Tap, Tap, Tap&quot; (you&apos;ll see why later), but as I was musing, &quot;knock, knock, knock, Penny&quot; kept coming to mind. The entire series of them. Then I found the image and here we are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently our class at JRS Code School took a dive into Functional Programming (FP). Im not going to get too deep into defining FP. For those of you not familiar with FP and would like to learn more I recommend bookmarking this post or adding to it your RSS feed and heading over to &lt;a href=&quot;https://fpjs.now.sh/docs/contents&quot;&gt;Functional Javascript&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&apos;ve made it this far, then there is a strong possibility that you have at some point struggled with a curried function. I struggled mightily with a few until being introduced to this tiny little tap function. Let&apos;s take a look at a curried function and then I&apos;ll show you how tap works. The following curried function uses Ramda functions compose, reduce, sort and map to return an array of a deck of playing cards in face value order. The compose function reads the other functions from right-to-left (if you prefer left-to-right you can use pipe) so the deck of cards array is passed into the map function which creates a new array of the card objects key &quot;code&quot;, which is then passed to sort to (obviously) sort it and finally it is passed to reduce where a new array of the card objects is returned in sorted order.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 650px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/49b61/curried-function.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 53.987730061349694%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAALABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIF/8QAFAEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAByJqQD//EABUQAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAB/9oACAEBAAEFAmv/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAY/Al//xAAXEAADAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBFB/9oACAEBAAE/ITY8P//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ08//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/ED//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/ED//xAAZEAACAwEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABEBExUWH/2gAIAQEAAT8QkCoA1lTj/9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image of curried function&quot;
        title=&quot;Image of curried function&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/6aca1/curried-function.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/d2f63/curried-function.jpg 163w,
/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/c989d/curried-function.jpg 325w,
/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/6aca1/curried-function.jpg 650w,
/static/92d0d61d5cbff78a468126776e8c2e1a/49b61/curried-function.jpg 752w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The above function currently works, but at one time it did not. How did I debug it? By using a function called tap. Let&apos;s take a look at it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 650px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/23313/tap-function.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 11.042944785276074%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAACABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEF/8QAFAEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAABx4AH/8QAFBABAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAQABBQJ//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPwE//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPwE//8QAFBABAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAQAGPwJ//8QAFRABAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAARD/2gAIAQEAAT8hb//aAAwDAQACAAMAAAAQ88//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/ED//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/ED//xAAWEAEBAQAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABECH/2gAIAQEAAT8Qau3/2Q==&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image of tap function&quot;
        title=&quot;Image of tap function&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/6aca1/tap-function.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/d2f63/tap-function.jpg 163w,
/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/c989d/tap-function.jpg 325w,
/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/6aca1/tap-function.jpg 650w,
/static/2b9e707db9dac64ee70ab88285ef2276/23313/tap-function.jpg 741w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;See the three taps? That&apos;s why the draft title of this post was Tap, Tap, Tap. But, you can call it whatever you like. Tap just seems a fitting name as it taps into the sequence of curried functions and gets called in the sequence along with the other functions. Here&apos;s a look at it put into action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span
      class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-wrapper&quot;
      style=&quot;position: relative; display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;  max-width: 650px;&quot;
    &gt;
      &lt;a
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-link&quot;
    href=&quot;/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/9bc89/curried-function-with-tap.jpg&quot;
    style=&quot;display: block&quot;
    target=&quot;_blank&quot;
    rel=&quot;noopener&quot;
  &gt;
    &lt;span
    class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-background-image&quot;
    style=&quot;padding-bottom: 60.73619631901841%; position: relative; bottom: 0; left: 0; background-image: url(&apos;data:image/jpeg;base64,/9j/2wBDABALDA4MChAODQ4SERATGCgaGBYWGDEjJR0oOjM9PDkzODdASFxOQERXRTc4UG1RV19iZ2hnPk1xeXBkeFxlZ2P/2wBDARESEhgVGC8aGi9jQjhCY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2NjY2P/wgARCAAMABQDASIAAhEBAxEB/8QAFgABAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAIF/8QAFAEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAP/aAAwDAQACEAMQAAAByJqQD//EABUQAQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABAB/9oACAEBAAEFAmv/xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAEDAQE/AT//xAAUEQEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAQ/9oACAECAQE/AT//xAAUEAEAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAg/9oACAEBAAY/Al//xAAWEAADAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAABIDH/2gAIAQEAAT8hMZ//2gAMAwEAAgADAAAAENPP/8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAwEBPxA//8QAFBEBAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAEP/aAAgBAgEBPxA//8QAGhAAAgIDAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAAREQITFRcf/aAAgBAQABPxBiFhLcljk//9k=&apos;); background-size: cover; display: block;&quot;
  &gt;&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;img
        class=&quot;gatsby-resp-image-image&quot;
        alt=&quot;Image of curried function with tap function inserted&quot;
        title=&quot;Image of curried function with tap function inserted&quot;
        src=&quot;/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/6aca1/curried-function-with-tap.jpg&quot;
        srcset=&quot;/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/d2f63/curried-function-with-tap.jpg 163w,
/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/c989d/curried-function-with-tap.jpg 325w,
/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/6aca1/curried-function-with-tap.jpg 650w,
/static/f27bc85d08140252cae518f0d018862c/9bc89/curried-function-with-tap.jpg 755w&quot;
        sizes=&quot;(max-width: 650px) 100vw, 650px&quot;
        style=&quot;width:100%;height:100%;margin:0;vertical-align:middle;position:absolute;top:0;left:0;&quot;
        loading=&quot;lazy&quot;
      /&gt;
  &lt;/a&gt;
    &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it do? Well, it simply accepts the return value of the previous function as a parameter, logs that parameter to the console and then returns that value to the next function allowing you to see the output at each step of the curried function. Pretty simple, right? It&apos;s been very helpful to me in understanding how a curried function works and how to alter my code accordingly to get the desired outputs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you can find use for this little tidbit. I know I have and in the process have limited the number of times I have had to look like dear, sweet Penny up above.&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[The Great Gatsby]]></title><description><![CDATA[My First Venture into Gatsby and GraphQL]]></description><link>https://scottsandman.github.io/the-great-gatsby/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">https://scottsandman.github.io/the-great-gatsby/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 Apr 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate><content:encoded>&lt;p&gt;Well, here we are. The first post of my recently constructed blog. How did we get here? It all started a couple weeks ago in JRS Code School video class session (pandemic and all). &lt;a href=&quot;https://robertwpearce.com/&quot;&gt;Robert Pearce&lt;/a&gt;, a Senior Software Engineer, took some time out of his day to speak with us prospective developers. One of the items he touched on during our discussion was &quot;learning in public&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought about what he meant by learning in public for a few days and was having a tough time wrapping my head around what it meant. Was I suppose to be on Facebook and Twitter all the time? I&apos;m not, by the way. So I reach out to Robert and asked. He responded with &quot;This will tell you everything you need to know: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.swyx.io/writing/learn-in-public/&quot;&gt;https://www.swyx.io/writing/learn-in-public/&lt;/a&gt; &quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Naturally, I clicked on the link and gained a much better understanding of what it meant to &quot;learn in public&quot;. It was something real and tangible and not just toodling around on social media. One of the first items on the list was to start a blog and discuss what I have been learning. Simple enough. I&apos;ve written blogs before. But where to start? Should I use my knowledge of MongoDB and Api&apos;s? We did just do a Travel Blog using those tools in class. I was having a difficult time figuring out how I was going to properly format the blog object when I passed it back into the HTML. I didn&apos;t really want it to be lumped all together and it didn&apos;t seem logical to have to write new JavaScript with each blog to format it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reached out to Robert, again. Robert&apos;s response, &quot;Start with HTML and CSS only and work your way up to using GatsbyJS.&quot; That&apos;s a quality plan. However, Robert doesn&apos;t really know me. You mention Gatsby to me once and it goes on my list of things to read about and eventually learn. Mention it twice and with the lure of working my way up to it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, I sat down to build a blog. Yes, using Gatsby. I found a tutorial online offered by Gatsby and I dug in. I should mention here that they also have a starter blog that you can clone from Github. That&apos;s not my style. A few hours in and I had broken it. The Blog that is. Errors everywhere. I&apos;m pretty certain I deleted some files and code I wasn&apos;t suppose to. Anyway, back to square one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took to Google again and that&apos;s when I found this tutorial by &lt;a href=&quot;https://ultimatecourses.com/blog/building-a-blog-with-gatsby-and-graphql&quot;&gt;Emma Bostian&lt;/a&gt;. Attempt number two was successful, obviously. But not only that, Emma did a really nice job of explaining ways to use GraphQl to set up your queries and handle your data. She didn&apos;t just show the code and explain it. She took the tutorial into GraphIQL and demonstrated how to build the queries. Kudos, Emma, that was very helpful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what did I learn in the past two days? Well, I reacquainted myself with ReactJS. It had been almost a year since I last worked on a project with it. Timing couldn&apos;t have been better as we are starting the React portion of our class this week. I learned that React with Gatsby and with GraphQL can make putting together a blog website fairly simple and eloquent. In more detail, I learned how to use my knowledge of APIs and turn them into a query. I learned how to set up those queries to be passed along into pages, and I also figured out how to navigate around in Gatsby a little bit. I liked it, a lot. This won&apos;t be my last adventure with it and most likely not the last time I break an app using it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hope you enjoyed the read. I do promise to get more technical as time goes on with actual code examples and such. I also plan on adding some more functionality to the app. In the meantime, if you have any comments or suggestions, please feel free to click on the Contact link above and shoot me an email.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To honor legendary news broadcaster Walter Cronkite, &quot;And that&apos;s the way it is, April 13th, 2020.&quot;&lt;/p&gt;</content:encoded></item></channel></rss>